National Visionary Leadership Project Interviews and Conference Collection AFC 2004/007
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series III: Interviews
  - Carmen de Lavallade oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2001-11-18, AFC 2004/007: 031
    The interview includes Carmen de Lavallade's memories of growing up in Los Angeles, California, taking dance classes and the influence of her cousin, dancer Janet Collins. She recalls performing with the Metropolitan Opera Ballet and the New York City Ballet and meeting her husband, Geoffrey Holder. She also discusses her friendship with Alvin Ailey and her careers as a choreographer and professor at Yale University.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655543
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (59 pages) (Box-folder 5/45)
    - Graphic Images, 4 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 26/353)
    - Moving Images, 3 videocassettes of 3 (Betacam SP) (90 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 031.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 031.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 031.MV.003
  - Ophelia DeVore-Mitchell oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2005-05-09, AFC 2004/007: 033
    Ophelia DeVore-Mitchell was a model, businesswoman and owner of the Ophelia DeVore School of Self-Development and Modeling.
    The interview includes Ophelia DeVore-Mitchell's memories of growing up in South Carolina and moving to New York City where she attended Hunter College High School. She recalls attending New York University, meeting her husband and her first modeling jobs. She discusses founding her modeling company to promote a better image of African Americans, changes in the advertising and fashion industries, and mentoring African American models and actresses.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655544
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (84 pages) (Box-folder 5/46)
    - Graphic Images, 7 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 26/354)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (DVCAM) (128 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 033.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 033.MV.002
  - David Dinkins oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2001-11-08, AFC 2004/007: 034
    David Dinkins was a New York State Assemblyman and the first African American mayor of New York.
    The interview includes David Dinkins' memories of growing up in Trenton, New Jersey, serving in the marines and attending Howard University and Brooklyn Law School. He discusses joining the Carver Democratic Club in Harlem and running for mayor of New York in 1989. He recalls several events during his time in office, including the Crown Heights riot, implementing the Safe Streets, Safe Cities program to reduce crime and cutting the budget. He also discusses losing the 1993 election to Rudy Giuliani and teaching public affairs at Columbia University.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655486
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (43 pages); 1 bound transcript (100 pages) (Box-folder 5/47-48)
    - Graphic Images, 12 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 26/355)
    - Moving Images, 4 videocassettes of 4 (Betacam SP) (120 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; 1 videocassette of 1 (VHS) (120 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. edited master; AFC 2004/007: 034.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 034.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 034.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 034.MV.004
  - David Driskell oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2002-04-10, AFC 2004/007: 035
    David Driskell was an art historian, curator and professor of African American art.
    The interview includes David Driskell's memories of growing up in North Carolina and attending Howard University. He recalls the segregation in Washington, D.C., meeting his wife, and his first teaching job at Talledega College, where he curated exhibitions of well-known artists. He discusses teaching at Fisk University, promoting and collecting African American art and his own work as a painter.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655522
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (71 pages) (Box-folder 5/49)
    - Graphic Images, 2 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in.; 1 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 26/356)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (Betacam SP) (180 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 035.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 035.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 035.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 035.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 035.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 035.MV.006
  - David Du Bois oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2002-12-11, AFC 2004/007: 036
    David DuBois was a writer, professor and social activist.
    The interview includes David DuBois' memories of growing up in Indiana, serving in the army in the Philippines during World War II and his political activism at Hunter College. He discusses how his mother met and later married his stepfather, W.E.B. DuBois, which led to his involvement in the Young Progressives of America and the Communist Party. He also discusses editing the newspaper of the Black Panther Party, his teaching career and his years living in Africa and China.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655487
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (74 pages) (Box-folder 5/50)
    - Graphic Images, 35 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in.; 4 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 26/357)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (Betacam SP) (180 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; 1 videocassette of 1 (DVCAM) (184 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. edited master; AFC 2004/007: 036.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 036.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 036.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 036.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 036.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 036.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 036.MV.007
  - Katherine Dunham oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2002-05-15, AFC 2004/007: 037
    Katherine Dunham was a dancer, choreographer and anthropologist.
    The interview includes Katherine Dunham's memories of growing up in the Chicago area during the Depression and studying anthropology at the University of Chicago. She discusses creating the Dunham Technique, her dance research in the Caribbean and her community arts programs in East St. Louis, Illinois.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655488
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (29 pages); 1 bound transcript (68 pages) (Box-folder 6/51-52)
    - Graphic Images, 5 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in.; 2 photographs: black and white; 5 x 7 in.; 23 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 26/358)
    - Moving Images, 5 videocassettes of 5 (Betacam SP) (150 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; 1 videocassette of 1 (DV) (186 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 037.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 037.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 037.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 037.MV.004
  - Joycelyn Elders oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2005-06-16, AFC 2004/007: 038
    Joycelyn Elders was a physician and the first African American U.S. Surgeon General.
    The interview includes Joycelyn Elders' memories of growing up in rural Arkansas and attending Philander Smith College. She recalls serving in the army as a physical therapist, attending medical school at the University of Arkansas and her early career as a pediatrician. She discusses her efforts to expand sex education, her friendship with Bill Clinton, and serving as Director of the Arkansas Department of Health and U.S. Surgeon General.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655501
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (39 pages) (Box-folder 6/53)
    - Graphic Images, 47 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 26/359)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (DVCAM) (128 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 038.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 038.MV.002
  - Ethel Ennis oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2006-09-11, AFC 2004/007: 039
    Ethel Ennis was a jazz singer and owner of the E&E Production Company.
    The interview includes Ethel Ennis' memories of growing up in Baltimore, Maryland, living in a housing project and learning to play piano. She recalls her first singing group, attending business school and performing with Benny Goodman in Europe. She also discusses performing on the Arthur Godfrey Show, founding the E&E Production Company with her husband and performing at Richard Nixon's inauguration.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655593
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (113 pages) (Box-folder 6/54)
    - Graphic Images, 86 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 27/360)
    - Moving Images, 3 videocassettes of 3 (DVC) (192 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 039.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 039.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 039.MV.003
  - Myrlie Evers-Williams oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2006-10-11, AFC 2004/007: 040
    Myrlie Evers-Williams was a civil rights activist and the chair of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, 1995-1998. She was the wife of Medgar Evers, a civil rights activist who was murdered in Mississippi in 1963.
    The interview includes Myrlie Evers-Williams' memories of growing up in Mississippi and her experiences with discrimination and harassment. She discusses meeting Medgar Evers at Alcorn A & M College and how they became involved in the civil rights movement, the harassment they faced, his murder and the related trials. She also discusses her move to California, attending Pomona College and becoming chairman of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655460
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (67 pages) (Box-folder 6/55)
    - Graphic Images, 95 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 27/361)
    - Moving Images, 8 videocassettes of 8 (Betacam SP) (240 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 040.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 040.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 040.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 040.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 040.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 040.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 040.MV.007; AFC 2004/007: 040.MV.008
  - Walter Fauntroy oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2004-02-19, AFC 2004/007: 041
    Walter Fauntroy was a minister, civil rights activist and president of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC). He was also D.C.'s first elected delegate to Congress.
    The interview includes Walter Fauntroy's memories of growing up in Washington, D.C. and attending Virginia Union University and Yale Divinity School. He discusses his work with Martin Luther King, Jr., the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) and the New Bethel Church of Washington, D.C. He also discusses planning the March on Washington, and running for delegate to Congress and mayor of Washington, D.C.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655461
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (55 pages) (Box-folder 6/56)
    - Graphic Images, 35 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 27/362)
    - Moving Images, 7 videocassettes of 7 (Betacam SP) (210 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 041.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 041.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 041.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 041.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 041.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 041.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 041.MV.007
  - Walter Fauntroy oral history interview conducted by Skip Coblyn, 2008-11-01, AFC 2004/007: 041b
    The interview includes Walter Fauntroy's opinions on the 2008 presidential election.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2011655239
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 041b.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 041b.MV.002
  - James Forman oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2004-08-04, AFC 2004/007: 042
    James Forman was a civil rights activist and leader of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). He also wrote several books and taught at American University.
    The interview includes James Forman's memories of growing up in Chicago and Mississippi and joining the Air Force. He discusses joining the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and several events related to the organization such as the Albany Movement and the internal division that led to the founding of the Black Panther Party. He also discusses founding the Unemployment and Poverty Action Committee, writing the Black Manifesto and his opinions on reparations for African Americans.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655462
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (86 pages) (Box-folder 6/57)
    - Graphic Images, 33 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in.; 3 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 27/363)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (Betacam SP) (180 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 042.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 042.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 042.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 042.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 042.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 042.MV.006
  - John Hope Franklin oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 1999-08-26, AFC 2004/007: 042a
    John Hope Franklin was a writer and professor of African American history.
    The interview includes John Hope Franklin's memories of growing up in Oklahoma and the Tulsa riot of 1921. He recalls attending Fisk University and his friendship with a white professor who encouraged him to go to Harvard University for his graduate degrees. He discusses teaching African American history at several universities and experiencing racism as a member of the Cosmos Club in Washington, D.C.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655503
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (27 pages); 1 bound transcript (51 pages) (Box-folder 6/58-59)
    - Graphic Images, 10 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 27/364)
    - Moving Images, 5 videocassettes of 5 (Betacam SP) (150 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; 1 videocassette of 1 (DV) (186 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. edited master; 1 videocassette of 1 (VHS) (120 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. edited master; AFC 2004/007: 042a.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 042a.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 042a.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 042b.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 042b.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 042c.MV.001
  - Frankie Muse Freeman oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2006-11-04, AFC 2004/007: 044
    Frankie Muse Freeman was a civil rights lawyer in Missouri. She was the first woman appointed to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights and helped found the Citizens' Commission on Civil Rights.
    The interview includes Frankie Muse Freeman's memories of growing up in Danville, Virginia and attending Hampton University and Howard University Law School. She discusses opening her own law practice in St. Louis, Missouri and working with the NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund on several civil rights cases related to school segregation and public housing. She also recalls President Johnson asking her to join the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights and her work with the commission in Mississippi.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655463
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (60 pages) (Box-folder 6/60)
    - Graphic Images, 9 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 27/365)
    - Moving Images, 3 videocassettes of 3 (DVCAM) (192 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 044.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 044.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 044.MV.003
  - Evelyn Granville oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2003-04-29, AFC 2004/007: 045
    Evelyn Granville was a mathematician, computer scientist and professor.
    The interview includes Evelyn Granville's memories of growing up in Washington, D.C. and attending Dunbar High school and Smith College. She recalls earning her Ph.D. in mathematics at Yale University, teaching at Fisk University and working at the National Bureau of Standards. She discusses working as a computer scientist at IBM, teaching at California State University and developing math curriculum for elementary school students.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2011655227
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (175 pages) (Box-folder 6/61)
    - Graphic Images, 21 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 27/366)
    - Moving Images, 5 videocassettes of 5 (Betacam SP) (150 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 045.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 045.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 045.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 045.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 045.MV.005
  - Samuel Gravely oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2002-10-31, AFC 2004/007: 046
    Samuel Gravely was the first African American admiral in the Navy.
    The interview includes Samual Gravely's memories of growing up in Richmond, Virginia and joining the navy at the beginning of World War II. He recalls passing the officer test, becoming the first African American to graduate from the navy's V-12 officer training program, and training other African Americans at segregated bases. He discusses his years out of the navy after World War II and being called back after the military was desegregated in 1948. He recounts his many tours of duty on ships including the USS Iowa, USS Taussig and his promotion to Vice Admiral.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655489
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (58 pages); 1 bound transcript (105 pages) with CD insert (Box-folder 7/62-63)
    - Graphic Images, 2 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color; 30 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in. (Box-folder 27/367)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (Betacam SP) (180 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 046.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 046.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 046.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 046.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 046.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 046.MV.006
  - Charles Green oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2004-05-18, AFC 2004/007: 047
    Charles Green was a Baptist minister in Virginia and Washington, D.C.
    The interview includes Charles Green's memories of growing up in Arlington, Virginia, where his father was a minister. He recalls attending Virginia Union University, serving in the segregated army during World War II and returning to pastor several churches in rural Virginia. He discusses meeting Martin Luther King, Jr., his initial involvement in the civil rights movement and his opinions on the drawbacks of desegregation for African Americans.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655490
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (25 pages) (Box-folder 7/64)
    - Graphic Images, 20 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in.; 2 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 27/368)
    - Moving Images, 5 videocassettes of 5 (Betacam SP) (150 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; 1 videocassette of 1 (DVCAM) (184 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. edited master; AFC 2004/007: 047.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 047.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 047.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 047.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 047.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 047.MV.006
  - Dick Gregory oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2002-04-29, AFC 2004/007: 048
    Dick Gregory was a comedian, public speaker, athlete and civil rights activist.
    The interview includes Dick Gregory's memories of growing up in St. Louis, Missouri, his struggles with learning to read and protesting segregated track meets. He recalls attending Southern Illinois University on a track scholarship, joining the army and his early comedy performances. He discusses working at the Playboy Club in Chicago, Illinois and appearing on the Tonight Show with Jack Paar. He also discusses his opinions on racism, education, the civil rights movement, and religion.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655504
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (112 pages) (Box-folder 7/65)
    - Graphic Images, 27 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 27/369)
    - Moving Images, 9 videocassettes of 9 (Betacam SP) (270 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; 1 videocassette of 1 (DV) (276 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. edited master; AFC 2004/007: 048.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 048.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 048.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 048.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 048.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 048.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 048.MV.007; AFC 2004/007: 048.MV.008; AFC 2004/007: 048.MV.009; AFC 2004/007: 048.MV.010
  - Robert Guillaume oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2002-04-15, AFC 2004/007: 049
    Robert Guillaume was a stage, film and television actor.
    The interview includes Robert Guillaume's memories of growing up in St. Louis, Missouri, serving in the army and attending Washington University. He recalls his early performances in musicals at the Karamu Theater in Cleveland, Ohio and on Broadway. He discusses his television roles on "Soap," "Benson" and "Sports Night," and his efforts to change how African Americans are portrayed in the media.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655524
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (48 pages) (Box-folder 7/66)
    - Graphic Images, 33 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 27/370)
    - Moving Images, 5 videocassettes of 5 (Betacam SP) (150 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 049.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 049.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 049.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 049.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 049.MV.005
  - Barbara Harris oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2002-11-15, AFC 2004/007: 050
    Barbara Harris was the first female bishop in the Episcopal Church.
    The interview includes Barbara Harris' memories of growing up in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, working in public relations and traveling through the segregated South for her job. She recalls her participation in the Episcopal Church and finding a community oriented parish and volunteering for several causes. She discusses her call to ministry, her process of ordination, and the opposition against her consecration as the first female bishop of the Episcopal Church.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655525
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (37 pages) (Box-folder 7/67)
    - Graphic Images, 12 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in.; 12 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 27/371)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (Betacam SP) (180 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 050.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 050.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 050.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 050.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 050.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 050.MV.006
  - Jimmy Heath oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2002-06-19, AFC 2004/007: 051
    Jimmy Heath was a saxophonist, composer and professor of music.
    The interview includes Jimmy Heath's memories of growing up in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania and learning to play saxophone. He recalls playing in many jazz bands with famous musicians including John Coltrane, Dizzy Gillespie, Charlie Parker and his brothers Percy and Albert. He also discusses his drug addiction, becoming a composer and teaching jazz at several colleges.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655505
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (57 pages) (Box-folder 7/68)
    - Graphic Images, 45 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 27/372)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (Betacam SP) (180 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; 1 videocassette of 1 (DV) (186 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. edited master; AFC 2004/007: 051.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 051.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 051.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 051.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 051.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 051.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 051.MV.007
  - Dorothy Height oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 1997-2001, AFC 2004/007: 052
    Dorothy Height was a social worker and civil rights activist. She was the president of National Council of Negro Women for forty years.